MARIO GUIDO

 \boxtimes : m.marioguido@gmail.com

2: +447745295019

Nationalities: Swiss, Argentinian, Italian

Languages: English (native), French (native), Spanish (native), German (beginner).

My research interests revolve mainly around criminal justice issues, particularly prison systems. Detention more widely is also of interest to me, having worked in NGOs dedicated to immigration detention-related matters. This focus is complemented by a broader interest in criminal law and social justice matters. I have experience teaching Criminal Law and open to teaching and designing any core modules in law.

EDUCATION

PhD University College London: Faculty of Law (Part-time) 2020 - Present

Dissertation: Returning once and for all: Building a Fair and Feasible Private Prison Labour System

Supervisors: Professor Virginia Mantouvalou; Professor Nicola Countouris

Previous Supervisors: Ms. Elaine Genders

LLM University College London, Faculty of Law: LLM Law 2017 - 2018

Grade: Merit

Dissertation: Private Prison Labour: Paradox or Possibility? Evaluating modern-day systems and establishing a model framework through the lens of the Forced Labour Convention

Supervisor: Ms. Elaine Genders

LLB University of Reading: LLB with Legal Studies in Europe

2013 - 2017

Grade: First Class (Hons)

Dissertation: To what extent does private sector involvement in the execution of prison labour comply with the United Kingdom's international obligations under the International Labour Organisation Forced Labour Convention, 1930 (No. 29): A Critical Enquiry

Supervisors: Professor Dr. Dimitrios Kyritsis & Dr. Stuart Lakin

University of Geneva, Faculty of Law (Switzerland) – Erasmus

February 2016 - July 2016

Certificate in Transnational Law

Grade: First Class (Hons)

Modules: Comparative Methodology: Tort Law; Current Issues of International Law Through the Case Law of International Courts and Tribunals; Introduction to the Law of Trusts; Internet & IT Law; International

Environmental Law

Uppsala University, Faculty of Law (Sweden) – Erasmus

August 2015 - January 2016

Grade: First Class (Hons)

Modules: European Labour Law; Criminal Law Theory

ACADEMIC WORK EXPERIENCE

University College London, Faculty of Laws

Graduate Lecturer Courses taught: Criminal law June 2024 - Present

My duties include teaching tutorials, marking examinations and coursework and lecturing.

University College London, Faculty of Laws

Summer School Lecturer

August 2024

During the 2024 UCL summer school, I gave a lecture on criminal law titled: "The right thing to do?"

Oxford Brookes University, School of Law and Social Sciences

Associate Lecturer

September 2023 – June 2024

Courses taught: Criminal law

My duties include leading seminar discussions, marking examinations and coursework; and ensuring consistent teaching across the module.

University College London, Faculty of Law, UK

LLM Dissertation Supervisor

Provision of 1:1 guidance, commentary and support to students' dissertations

April 2024 - June 2024

LLB Student Mentor

Annual mentoring LLB Students at University College London

September 2022 - June 2023

• Provision of 1:1 guidance, commentary and support to students' dissertations

Global Detention Project, Switzerland

Research Fellow

March 2020 – September 2020

- Helped launch the "COVID-19 Global Immigration Detention Platform" and drafted over 100 country updates.
- Assisted in drafting country profiles concerning countries in the South and Central American region.
- Drafted information requests to Government Institutions, NGO's, IGO's and academics.
- Collaborated in the design and development of new data fields on the GDP database.

Research Intern

October 2019 - March 2020

- Identified gaps in information on the GDP database and conducted research into national detention legislation.
- Developed data and drafted 4 country profiles on immigration detention systems in South America.

Centre for Intellectual Property & Policy Management, Bournemouth University

June 2015

• Participated in data-collection for a university project on "geo-blocking" and its implication as regards European free movement provisions.

PEDAGOGICAL APPROACH

- My teaching philosophy is founded on creating an inclusive educational environment that equips students with a
 deep understanding and curiosity of the subject at hand, questioning the status quo. Drawing from my experiences
 as an Associate Lecturer at Oxford Brookes, where I lead seminar discussions in criminal law, and my role as an
 LLB Student Mentor at University College London, I prioritise student engagement and participation.
- In the classroom, I emphasise a student-centred approach encouraging critical analysis, debate, and fostering a collaborative learning atmosphere. By intertwining my academic expertise from my doctoral studies with practical insights gained from my work with several NGOs, I strive to provide students with a holistic perspective on criminal justice matters when teaching criminal law. Through this approach, I aim to nurture their analytical thinking and legal research skills.

WORK EXPERIENCE

International Detention Coalition, UK

November 2022 - December 2023

Europe Programme Officer

- Participated in the mapping and creating the research framework for an East Africa mapping project.
- Organised and led sessions at the European Alternatives to Detention Network meeting in 2023.
- Identified research methodologies and gathered data through desk review and interviews for an impact study.

Global Detention Project, Switzerland

October 2020 - November 2022

 $Project\ Coordinator\ (Global\ Immigration\ Detention\ Observatory\ Project)$

- Approved more than 4,000 data entries by partners onto the GDP database.
- Led database trainings for 6 partner organisations and provided continuous support throughout the project.
- Drafted submissions on immigration enforcement issues to United Nations Treaty Bodies (CAT, CMW, CRC, CERD).
- Coordinated and facilitated the Committee on Migrant Workers Information Session with Civil Society.

Children and Families Across Borders, UK

April 2019 – September 2019

Inter-country Caseworker

- Handled a caseload of international child protection cases (child protection alerts, record/welfare checks, home visits) originating from ISS partners and UK Local Authorities.
- Provided advice on the CFAB Advice line to NGO, local authorities or individuals on international child protection processes.
- Coordinated work with International Social Service and CFAB partners and established a close working relationship with partners from France and Spain due to local language capabilities.

AIRE Centre, UK

November 2018 - March 2019

Legal Caseworker

- Led the drafting of the AIRE submission for the Blueprint Consultation on Women in Prison 2018 and the Centre's submission for the UK Review of the UN Convention Against Torture.
- Conducted legal research in support of human trafficking cases and wrote legal advice letter.

Matrix Chambers, UK

April 2015

• Shadowed Karon Monaghan QC at the UK Supreme Court during the case of Essop v Home Office.

Journal Articles

• Guido, M. "Beyond Profit: A model framework for ethical and feasible private prison labour" (2024) Vol. 15(3) European Labour Law Journal, pp.581-596.

Approximate Word Count: 7,000

- Guido, M. "Trabalho Prisional Privado: Paradoxo ou Possibilidade? Avalição Dos Sistemas Modernos e
 Estabelecimento De Um Modelo de Estrutura Através Das Lentes Da Convenção Sobre Trabalho Forçado" (2023)
 Vol.6, Trabalho e restrição de liberdade: fronteiras entre a restauração da dignidade e a exploração da indignidade,
 ENAMAT, pp.251-295. (Translated by Fernanda Potiguara Carvalho).
 Approximate Word Count: 12,500
- Guido, M. "Trabalho Prisional Privado: Paradoxo ou Possibilidade? Avalição Dos Sistemas Modernos e Estabelecimento De Um Modelo de Estrutura Através Das Lentes Da Convenção Sobre Trabalho Forçado" (2020) No. 4 (2), Revista de Direito da Universidade de Brasília, pp.137-180. (Translated by Fernanda Potiguara Carvalho). Approximate Word Count: 12,500
- Guido, M. "Private prison labour: paradox or possibility? Evaluating modern-day systems and establishing a model framework through the lens of the Forced Labour Convention", (2019), 8(2) UCL Journal of Law and Jurisprudence, pp.26-54.

Approximate Word Count: 12,500

Guido, M. "Privatización del trabajo penitenciario: ¿paradoja o posibilidad? Una evaluación de los sistemas modernos y consideración de un sistema bajo la óptica del Convenio de Trabajo Forzoso de la Organización Internacional del Trabajo", (2019), La Ley (Thomson Reuters): Revista Derecho del Trabajo, No. 4 (III), pp.808-827.
 Approximate Word Count: 12,500

Reports

Cooper, H. & Guido, M. "Pathways to Change: A Review of Advocacy and Influencing in Europe, 2017-2023"
 International Detention Coalition, December 2023, https://atdnetwork.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/EATDN-Impact-Study-2023.pdf

Approximate Word Count: 20,000

Blogs

• Guido, M. "Beyond Profit: A model framework for ethical and feasible private prison labour" Human Rights in Context, September 2024.

Approximate Word Count: 2,400

Cooper, H. & Guido, M. "Driving Change and Ensuring Sustainable Impact: Reflections from the 2023 European
Alternatives to Detention Network meeting" European Alternatives to Detention Network, 29 June 2023,
https://atdnetwork.org/news/driving-change-and-ensuring-sustainable-impact-reflections-from-the-2023-european-alternatives-to-detention-network-meeting/

Approximate Word Count: 1,500

PERSONAL PROJECTS

Prison Labour Mapping Project

 Personal comparative mapping project of prison labour systems in Europe alongside the Institute for Crime & Justice Policy Research from Birkbeck University – August 2024 – Present

Reform Radar

 Creation of 'Reform Radar' in 2023. Online repository of good practices that aim to rehabilitate and reintegrate prisoners. The database is currently under development.
 August 2023 – Present

CONFERENCES, WORKSHOPS & LECTURES

- 'Reassessing Private Prison Labour: Towards rehabilitation, reintegration and fairness' at University of East London, School of Business and Law February 2024
- 'The Labour and Social Security Rights of Captive Workers' Workshop at University College London, Faculty of Law – July 2023
- 'European Consultation on Strategic Litigation on Strategic Litigation & Legal Advocacy for Refugee and Migrant Rights' at the OSCE Office for Democratic Institutions and Human Rights (ODHIR), Warsaw, Poland

PROFESSIONAL COURSES & TRAININGS

- IMPACTUM Research Group & the Global Campus of Human Rights: Summer Course: Human Rights and Persons Deprived of Liberty. 18-21 June 2024.
- International Detention Coalition: Alternatives to Detention IDC Online Training Toolkit. January 2023
- Council of Europe HELP / UNHCR online course on Alternatives to Immigration Detention. January 2023
- Coram Children's Legal Centre: Rights of Children and Young People in the Immigration System Training. June 2019
- **RBKC:** Multi-Agency Safeguarding and Child Protection (Level 1 & 3). May 2019
- Council of Europe: HELP Course on Refugee and Migrant Children. November 2018 March 2019
- Amicus ALJ: Death Penalty Training. April 2014

REFERENCES AVAILABLE UPON REQUEST

- Ms. Elaine Genders, Reader in Criminology, University College London.
- Professor Virginia Mantouvalou, Professor of Human Rights and Labour Law, University College London.
- Chris Lloyd, Senior Lecturer in Law and LLB Subject Coordinator, Oxford Brookes University.
- Carolina Gottardo, Executive Director, International Detention Coalition.
- Michael Flynn, Director of the Global Detention Project.
- Carolyn Housman, CEO of Children and Families Across Borders.

RECOMMENDATION LETTERS

- Dr Steven Vaughan, Associate Professor, University College London.
- Steve Banks, Associate Professor, University of Reading.
- Stefan Eberhard, Director and Secretary, Obserson Abels SA.